[Music]
hello guys
hello sir welcome back
thank you you are the first person
to make a second visit send space now so
i'm the first second
i'm looking for a joke about that but
for once one isn't coming
we'll let it rna we'll let it marinate
exactly
um it's good to be on
i like what you're doing yeah
well how did you find the the zack stein
uh conversation that was great
it was really great like
well he's just such an interesting guy
like he's just he's just an interesting
guy and he's operating at a level
of things that's not the stuff that he
said about um
paradigms right and
the difference between being you know
being of a paradigm and
and having letting it be object allows
you to then speak
as i would say like speak the language
of your cult in the language of another
cult
in a second as a practice right in in
some sense which is
was a relief to hear with with
understanding his of you know his
affinity with integral
that's what because that's one of the
i've always had a heart
a little bit of a hard time with in i
don't know if it's integral per se but
integral
folks um more the culture around
integral right is uh uh
i just i always had this sense in which
they were using terms right
without without what it takes to
to have those terms right like
so it was as if they were deeply
thinking about things profoundly but
there was a sense in which they just
kind of picked it up
and started labeling things in terms of
this and i just always found it a bit
empty for me
so like hearing um hearing him talk
about i got
much more of a sense of like no integral
um
is a way of thinking right
isn't necessarily a product of the
thought but a way of thinking
like he was really you know applying it
in a certain sense i really like that
yeah i had this the same experience uh
the whole like red
the red and the green and all of the
different times that they have and
um but i did end up reading ken wilber's
book
uh brief history of everything i think
is
like one of the first ones and it's
written as a
a dialogue and it's pretty good
but for me it's really i just extracted
the
spirit of integral which is uh
sort of transcend and include
effectively
um and that every stage of development
has some fruits in it
and has some issues in it um
yeah which is the big conceit of
the you know modernity and
time that we're living in is that we
just brush away
yeah or we pick and choose
yeah it's a good conversation and he's
he's very high level
um and i'm sure there'll be some
continuity
with what we talk about today um and
probably some continuity with the
conversation with john as well yeah
johnson could be in that conversation he
seemed to
really key in on your your
your sensibility around christianity
okay i think he really connected with
you there
yeah it definitely felt like something
slotted into place
i was having a commonality of background
and me kind of
having been on a long track with it and
taking quite a
playful uh approach to it
yeah having been through um
you know having journeyed in the the
world of psychedelics
you can begin to read um
religious texts and mystical texts
through the lens of those experiences
and you can kind of
you know the whole like daniel
schmucktenberger like
listen for the signal and the noise um
took a long time to get to a point where
i was open enough to attempt
that yeah but i have sort of begun to
attempt that in kind
and uh i listened for the signal and so
when i read about
um strange occurrences and uh
you know tongues of fire and all of this
stuff i try and
think like well what could that have
actually been in relationship to the
weirdest experiences i've had
and yeah it's
it takes something to do that doesn't it
like
you had to what i'm hearing you say is
you had to come through to
being able to do that because there's
something about
christianity that
it's it i don't know what it is it's
it's there's something so familiar
in um in some of the terms
that like come with all this baggage
right that
on some level m most modernity has been
pushing against
for a long time so it's like it takes
something
to push past that that thing into the
actual intelligibility that i think
originally that all that came from
yeah and off the back of that
conversation i had a
couple of different people reach out and
had some
non-recorded conversations as well with
one guy who's uh actually jehovah's
witness
and another guy who's seems to have had
a very similar track to me
um yeah very fruitful
a lot of interesting stuff about kind of
discontinuities between what's being
said and what's being embodied
uh that seemed to be a very emergent
theme of it
was was experiences of communities and
so forth where there was
a doctrinal set of values and then there
was what was
actually embodied yeah it's like
you can almost train you can train
yourself or you can be enculturated in a
context
of care um or of love
or of intimacy which is not actually
afforded by
your capacity or the context um
my dad was telling me you know these a
lot of these prayer groups they just
kind of stick a bunch of people
together and get them talking in this
really intimate way without actually
having that natural
friendship um which would be the basis
of it
so there's kind of a difference between
an organically developing
thing and then the institution of church
and then there's a lot of feeling that
that there's a certain brokenness
which is a part of the togetherness
of it and that the institution itself is
somehow sustained by
you not fully developing beyond that
yeah yeah totally
i wonder if this has something to do
with
you know i heard um johannes's
uh teacher his professor at college
talk about this and i've i've also been
reading his book
the principles of philosophy
which sounds like such a generic
ordinary
title red book right it's just like
looks like i don't know maybe a boring
textbook of some kind
but man talk about talk about the
reading
the reading of which you end up reading
one of those experiences where you're
reading you know
as you're reading you're you're hearing
about the
frame of reference that is reading that
you didn't know was the frame
right it's like one of those those
experi those hermenetic experiences of
of
like he just abstracted out the
underlying intelligibility upon which my
thinking was thinking that thought which
when you do that something ecstatic kind
of happens
the whole book is like that um he's it's
amazing when you take that stuff
really seriously like language and
intelligibility
but one of the things he was talking
about in one of the videos
with johannes i think it was on the end
was the end of philosophy i think it's
it was that one where
it was this
you know you could say
pre before the pre-socratics
right um
language and thinking was more
our relationship to it was one in which
was in the mytho-poetic sense like that
language
gave us shelter right
inside of being right
so so the
homer and mythology and those kinds of
things is where the with
where the language was one in which you
found it
you found shelter in the world and it
held you
right in these in these images
and then around with the pre-socratics
all of a sudden
if they see if i can put this get this
correct
man started to think
being as a whole right and everything
everything that we stand on is
predicated on that
right the b is heidegger would say the
being of beings
and in once we could start to think and
abstract out
the sense in which
what all beings partake a certain
different relationship to being started
to to come and come into existence right
to the world because now we could have a
relationship
with being right through our cognition
through our thinking
and and if you think about
what that real what we're in
relationship with through thinking
the being is like the category of
categories right it's the
it's the thing upon which every thing
that you can name
right its intelligibility is based on
that
so all of a sudden man now
has access to to to understand something
the understanding of which
can can literally
have the world show up based on an
understanding
that's basically philosophy
and then it was about right then it was
about where where
in some sense the standing
right or the holding
that found shelter now
in a certain sense man started to do
this thing where he could
hold kind of you could say hold himself
in standing relationship with being
right and and it rather than the being
finding itself immersed in a kind of a
mythical world
all of a sudden we could we took that
sheltering
and or that stick that that gathering
holding and could hold ourselves
right in and have an inquiry into that
relationship
and then what's interesting is like and
that's all the stuff around
right the understanding of being thought
as foosis
right the thatness the the
the sense in which um
being could could could uh
you could say disclose in a in a
spontaneous
disclosure that wasn't given by
wasn't given through apprehension of our
senses but we could start to see
a logos behind it and so
that which at which you didn't see you
could actually
start to grab hold of and realize
was a deeper pattern embodied through
all of the things that you saw
and um and then in plato as it moved on
it became more of um i think
i idios edios
one of those greek terms but it more it
was more about the sense of
the what-ness of being what is being
right that's when you start to get in
the talk of the good
right and all that stuff with with plato
but then
and this is kind of tying it back to
christianity what's really interesting
when you think about this then
then christianity started to come online
and and
the revealed truth right the
the more of the mythical poetic sense of
it right
then being became the supreme being
and then thinking after that in in
in theology was born where philosophy
now became
not something that was grappling with
what
or how right or that
there was being instead
being was seen as god
the supreme being and then all thinking
was to
derive its truth to reveal it
right so in some sense like thinking no
longer went to
and grappled with the sense of being and
that's the whole thing about theology
right and the
it's like these the wedding of these two
sensibilities
and so it's kind of interesting to think
about it like that
and i you know you get that because in
in uh
i i've been thinking quite a bit about
this
there is something relieving to imagine
what a medieval town was
right like the the idea of the medieval
time
is like the highest point in the town is
the church
so you're constantly reminded of what
right who's in charge or or the or the
the most
infinite point of reference and then
everything
points back to that almost like a
mandala right everything everyone does
right is is in relationship to that
in his the customs the manners the
buildings
the architecture everything is
disclosing this intelligibility
doesn't that sound nice
well it's it's certainly
one of the sort of experiments that i
ran recently
with a friend was to go for a a
leisurely walk
in london and we went to southwark
cathedral
um and in the cathedral we kind of
stepped into this sort of side room
um like a prayer room or whatever
my friend is um pakistani but went to a
christian like a english catholic uh
you know like one of those old schools
that had like a
14th century chapel on the grounds and
stuff so he had a relationship to it as
well
and we started kind of talking about
religion
um and the death of god and all of this
stuff and then as we're walking around
i began to look at the stained glass
mirrors
and try to put myself really fully into
the mindset of the
especially of the medieval peasant
for whom that was the
highest quality of special effects
psychedelic experience known
and there's a weird kind of illumined
quality to these
to these symbolic representations which
has like a timelessness to it as well
right um it really gathers doesn't it
when you really get present to those to
that artwork or to the
the stained glass or the symbol i mean
everything about it
is just so if you really like
meditate on it or you really give
yourself to it man it
it is there's something deeply
organizing to it
but in this in this strange way where on
some level
it's also got an explanation because
it's this
it's um it's also backed by all this
thinking which is what the
theologians just did right he wasn't
thinking
it was a different kind of thinking it
was that there was some there was a
that there was the revealed truth of god
right
and thought couldn't you couldn't not
think that right that was just kind of
the point and then everything and then
so truth was
about getting showing how rationality
rationally that that was true so
everything its measure
was measured by this kind of mono
literally monotheistic
center
yeah i've been getting into a lot about
the sort of
oneness and twoness of reality
and i don't know if i can even better
articulate it than that but kind of
trying to hold
that aspect of monotheism of of the
unity of everything
and then the twoness
the multiplicity of things as well um
and this has really been fed by
my kind of inquiries into nature um
both of the natural world and and the
human you know the human body as well
um there's all of these different things
when you're looking at a
um when you're looking at a tree and
you're contemplating
a tree there's a way in which you can
perceive it as like this one
sort of solid thing um you know you have
the
this and you have a merging out and then
you have the roots going down but
um those roots split
down so much into such minute sort of
uh tendril like interaction with the
soil that at some point they're really
not really distinguished
yeah and so too with the leaves coming
from the
um branches down onto the ground
uh this is something that's revealed a
lot more in an urban environment
because there's nowhere really for the
leaves to go so you see that
you know like a violet covered tree and
then you see this
surround on the ground on some
like non-jew level this part
and this part are not separate things
yeah oh yeah
so i'm i'm bringing in a lot of
different pieces into this conversation
and we are like in so many different
territories and i'm wondering how
to gather them together and probably the
best way for me to do that is to just
presence them
um and see
see what you make of it really um
because we were talking a little bit
before i was talking i mentioned this
with john actually
um about the kind of
satin setting psychedelic nature of
reality
um of during the covid
during kobit a number of people jordan
hall
and uv ivanova and other people were
saying
the veil is thinner now
um which is very curious to me
what what is the veil i think the veil
is something like
um consensus reality
and and the revealing of that is what i
talked about with john with this
kind of cyclist emerging into my field
of vision
and for a moment it's just like this
amorphous
thing and then it actually manifests as
what it is
and since then i've had a number of
similar experiences with
um dropping in on conversation as well
like i was in greece on the metro and i
had
some ambient conversation and my brain
interpreted it as like some english
women speaking and it was just
absolutely not the case
but i realized something about my
um disposition and associations
interpreted um what i couldn't quite
make out
um and so
we have that occurring we have this kind
of
revealing going on in the day-to-day as
we're walking around
and then we have young
and his argumentation about dreams which
i've been reading
um which by the way is interesting in
itself because i had read man and his
symbols a number of years ago
and found it to be i had kind of read it
in my academic
um harvesting kind of mode of reading
and so i got almost nothing from it
because i was just like
you know blitz and extract kind of
relationship to text
but since reading heidegger
um oh yeah you we gotta talk about your
what that was like i'm very near to the
end of being in time which you
yeah kindly are not so kindly sort of
recommended for me
that has completely retrained my
relationship to reading rening
because it's so bloody difficult in in
large part
um you have to read it very closely
and very slowly and you really are
deducing what
is being expressed yeah and so when i
read jung the second time
i read it in the fashion informed by
this and
the text revealed itself in a very
different way
yeah um it was as if jung
was writing something in the words and
the content and then there was something
else going on
um and as he was talking about the
unconscious
and the unconscious associations and the
relationship
of the conscious mind
to dreaming and the unconscious
i felt my present reality become
stranger
i'm more curious right
i like how stranger
means good
to you more of that i.e
go towards that stranger yes
pause one second i might there's a
there's a spa that's going on
yeah i think what
what you just said i had just sparkled
for me so let's i just want to see what
that was
um when you talked about
reading being in time that
it it it required a reading
that was really like i think he said he
reintroduced you
to a different way of reading
because every part of it
right one is just really rigorous and
difficult right
however something
almost beyond what just the text said
right had something shine through it
it's difficult to put into words and
it's difficult to reduce down to what
just what was said in the text in such a
way
that when you read another author in the
same
way of reading which is interesting i
want to get at what what that way is
it what he said is jung
disclosed something
different than the first time you read
you
that disclosure right i think is if you
think about it what is our
access to the world it discloses itself
right i think the thing that's
interesting to me is that there's a
there's a way that reading and this has
really been my experience too
of there's there's something going on
with reading
in the way that you read that
seems to touch on something that is
um i think symbolically and literally
the our relationship with the world that
that there's a there's a way i can
participate with the world that is
that comes through its disclosure comes
through the way i participate with it
such that i can the way that i
relate to to young
10 years ago versus the way i relate to
young
today is what it reveals the world
really really differently if you ask me
this is this is what this is what's
worth thinking about this is what's
worth
doing as human beings and this is what
human beings are
right these were world disclosures
and i think that the veil
um perhaps the veil that jordan is
talking about
that's thinner is that
is that the world can't make sense
anymore
like in other words the text the
information on the text
isn't going to make have the world make
sense to you anymore
right your way of reading you can't just
you can't just read it like you used to
be able to read it read it
for information and take it as given and
right
nominalize it and then live your life
being substantiated within
those nominalizations and just you know
idle idling along
that there's enough stuff going on right
that doesn't make sense
that requires um i think it reveals our
deep
the deep way in which our reading
participates in what's being disclosed
in the text
yeah there's a real sort of
inter-subjective
reality being revealed in this
experience
which necessitates us letting go of the
notion that
we're all reading the same book
because on some level we're not um
yeah it's informed by our experiences
but it's more deeply informed by
our relationship to the world um
and so this way of reading is also
something which is transpiring outside
it's transpiring in the way that i'm
walking around
in berlin um
well it's quite exhausting actually
because i used to be able to blitz
through enormous amounts of text
um because i was goal oriented
and i trained in a certain way for my
university studies
which was a kind of extraction
methodology um
to boil down and extract what was useful
but that presupposes that i know
what's useful or i know what i'm looking
for
um and when you come up against
these texts these deep philosophers you
don't very quickly you no longer know
what it was that you were looking for
um and something else is
shining through but it's kind of
necessitating you to like
move with it um
in a different way yeah and then when
you're going out into the world you're
experiencing the world in a different
way as well
yeah yeah and you're
what i heard you say with heidegger is
that
you emphasize the difficulty of it
so there's some relationship with
suffering you have to suffer
it right
yes and that was not something that i
was
on board for before right but for
whatever reason some crazy reason
yeah like guys really into heidegger i
gotta check this out and i read and
started reading it i was like well
i trust you and so i trust that there's
something
there's a there there um and so i began
struggling through and it's i've been
with this book now for many many months
um and i can't just go and finish it
like i can with another book because
and i get i can't i can't go into it
with a goal orientation of like i'm
going to get
through the chapter or through to the
end because getting through
one page of three pages of this book
is really energy intensive
yeah yeah totally
and if you feel into what is it so on so
on some level if we look at that
so here's your
you read something in me like i was
wondering if like in a certain sense
what like i is a symbol
right to you right you entrusted
that gave he went ah there must be
something here because he's really into
that even though i look at that
stuff and i'm like what the hell is that
it's like
but like if he's if he's seeing
something
and i would imagine on some level like
the thing that you
see going on in me is that there's a way
that
that there's a world disclosure that
happens
right and so there's i would imagine on
some level
it was um and i really relate to that
like
like so many books that i've ended up
reading is not because
i looked at those things and thought to
myself oh that looks like a good thing
it's no
like you know some mentor of mine was
really into it or they said this
and usually usually what i was trusting
was trusting them but what does that
mean right i think in
in in these cases it really did have to
do with
now that i'm thinking about it there's a
way that the world shows up for them
and discloses for them that when i
participate in that world
i am somehow more than i than i would be
if i wasn't um
and well so this is interesting too
is that when i first saw you on rebel
wisdom
like a couple of years back probably i
saw a guy
and i was like i
didn't make anything of you i didn't it
didn't strike me
nothing happened but then later on
as you started popping up more and doing
interviews with other people
uh it was almost as if you were revealed
in relationship to them yeah
which is totally analogous to what was
going on with young
and my it's
so my relationship with reading has
changed but also my relationship with
the selection of what i read has also
changed in a similar way to what you
suggested
it feels more that i'm on an intuitive
breadcrumb trail yeah and i'm listening
to the world um
for where to go next
and then i follow that intuition
and the book comes and i start reading
it and then there's something in there
which really
comes with me and that intuition is kind
of confirmed
in a way you said something just then
listen i listen to the world
what what do you mean by listening
i think it's more of a sitting back
and allowing for the arising of
rather than an active like a verb like a
like an act of doing or
catching or seeking um
it's more like allowing the thing to
arrive to you
yeah totally and how would you say
is it listening
that has
what it i'll like this is it
how do you know what is worthy of
listening to
so like on some level listening is
basically allowing like letting the
world disclose itself to you
right is it listening
that here's the here's
here's what to hear
like i think this is what we're kind of
get like getting at is like oh
how do i
that's what what you're touching on now
kind of is a
is something ontological or some sort of
horizon
which brings into question free will
and and touches on
this sense that my
decision-making and more specifically my
listening and what
um
what arises as salient to me
is informed by such a web of
associations um
is informed by a kind of story or
um a collection of narrative
arcs we could perhaps delineate in my
life
up to the point of those things
happening which drew that out
you know when i first was
drawn to start looking and understanding
islam
that of course made very little sense
based on my life and background up to
that point
yeah and yet there was something
captivating um
which was drawing me into it and i was
coming to understand something
yeah something was so alive about when
you talked about
captivating that
whatever that is whatever that sense is
i really
i i think i owe my everything i call
good in my life is a function of that
right everything i really value and
has this quality of i'm going along and
then
something calls to me
like in fact the more it doesn't make
sense the more
if in fact it calls beyond my
sense my sense making if you will in
fact it's precisely what
gathers my attention and it is it is a
captivation
right it's uh there's something this has
been always been
this is like a big mystery to me you
know on how do i know
when something captures and glows to me
sparkles to me and
i then i go i start to i start to engage
with
it i start to be captivated start to
find myself giving over to it
20 years later i look back and realize
right a whole style of life that was
articulated
through the process of this becoming
disclosed
but how did i know if i didn't
understand it
beforehand how did i know to be
interested in it
this is like one of the mysteries to me
and
i've definitely been on a
process of um
leaning into that um
which means having
a like more relationship to not knowing
and less relationship to knowing at the
level of
who i am where i'm going
um which previously for me like someone
would ask me how i'm doing and i would
tell them
what i'm doing and you know i'd be like
well i'm doing this in order to do this
and so forth and so forth
and uh this was the kind of um
relationship to self and to
world into future
so you have to loosen up first of all in
order
for this to transpire and there's a lot
of ways to do it
one of them is you're curious and you
seek out
experiences which
um take you to the edge of your
intelligibility
um and
and those those are very revealing
another is that
life comes and meets you in some
devastating way
uh um tragedy knocks at your door
um your will
at least in my case my will
was exhausted at in relationship
to the world it was as if the world
provided me with the circumstance in
which i could
drive and drive and drive and drive with
my willpower until it was completely
undone by circumstance um
and then you're left in an interesting
position after that
when when you're in the uh
to when you're in the tragic state you
do like you develop a more of a
relationship to not knowing as well
um not in the least because you don't
know when you're gonna
be able to move out of that state
but also because the characteristic of
that state
is a contraction
of all those future plans and everything
that your identity rested upon
so it really brings everything in
um in a way that reduces
how much reality is disclosed to you and
reduces what's interesting um
and makes everything really bloody
difficult but um
so those are some of the pieces but
one one that's quite particularly
strange
is is how far do we take this um
listening to world um
you know there's that we can take it
into well maybe
my relationship to thinkers or
authors or books you know instead of
like
reading a list of what other people say
you should read
you're listening for it and then kind of
like all that seems like it might be an
interesting piece of the puzzle and then
you
go towards that but then you can also
begin to
have this just in the world
you know i've had experiences where i'm
looking at things written on people's
t-shirts
and you know little
signs and this is something that i also
hold very lightly
um and it's something that comes out of
the psychedelic experience almost
certainly
is that you start to see things which
have a certain
um sign like quality to them
and you're just like oh that's
interesting you entertain it
but you don't the key is that when
things when strange things occur
you don't just sort of
um reactively
shut that out in order to maintain the
coherence of the
of the view that you have you just allow
it to be there
um
and that that begins to imbue your whole
relationship to the world
and then you can be following that
intuitive impulse which is what i've
been doing i feel like with this whole
last six months
more and more and now it's beginning to
produce beautiful fruit um
so it's it seems to confirm itself
um and one
uh teacher of mine someone that you know
to said to me when we were speaking uh
like a homeless guy came up to us and
started
sort of blabbing about some random stuff
you know he clearly looked like he was
washed out um
but the teacher that i was with looked
at him
fully listened to what he said responded
to him and then came back to me and said
like
i wouldn't have been surprised if he
told me exactly what i needed to hear
yeah and that seems to me to come from a
place of
you're not just relating to individuals
and objects so to speak you're relating
to
world and world is
in a kind of communication with you
not in a very clear way and not in a
concrete
way more in the way that
um that comes about from
developing a relationship to your dreams
um
and that kind of thing getting getting
that dream interpretation in
uh can begin to loosen up your
relationship to
conscious reality and then begin to look
for
well one of one of the things that jung
talks about in
man and his symbols is that um
day-to-day objects and little things can
take on really uncanny
importance and be imbued
with deep deep meaning um
and as you spoke on your video about
heraclitus
what was it heretics yeah um
this sentiment which when you lean into
the logos
or you are listening for the logos
[Music]
reality itself can start to seem to
emanate objects and things seem to
[Music]
hint to you that there's something a
little more to them than what they
actually show up to be
the edges are kind of illumined um
and what i have been coming to
understand is that
the the greater you're leaning into that
frontier the greater you're experiencing
um objects more and more
to the extent that you could
be um you know sort of
contemplating the deepest meanings of
your life whilst looking at a
flower or a glass of water or something
um
this is actually like a going out deeper
into the world and deeper into self
at the same time and the two are
becoming less and less
um distinguished
and then this is where the whole veil
thing
this is how we can begin to understand
the veil notion
and the and the way in which reality
itself is
always psychedelic in the sense
of psychedelia mind manifesting
we experience reality as a manifestation
of mind
how we interpret mind is another matter
but this is
this is um most apparent and simple
simply put if you're very very hungry
and you haven't had your dinner and
you're walking around
reality seems to become very very much
reduced
the color the color is drawn out and
your capacity to relate to everything is
drawn out
and then what speaks to you is smells of
food and
right everything becomes in terms of
your hunger
yeah and if you are
if you have a uh trauma in your past
associated with a certain thing
then that becomes more salient in
reality to you
but it doesn't just become more salient
um
the fact that you know
supposing that i was
subject to some act of cruelty
by um a sports coach
it's not just that i'm now more
okay it's it's not just that you're more
anxious towards people who
trigger this um memory
it's that this memory somehow draws out
that aspect in reality towards you as
well
um this is the
this is the uh
this is what i was really uncovering
with the landscape of trauma
was that
our traumas really shape our reality and
the way that we
experience it and draw things out of
reality toward us
um like the world comes to meet us in
relationship
to our trauma uh insofar as we have not
fully
understood it and worked through it uh
yeah especially
especially wouldn't you say with trauma
um especially in the for
having right
like because i often thought about this
it's like i
you know if i looked at you both my
parents were were
were addicts and alcoholics and stuff
and so there was like a lot of that
you know a lot of yelling and violence
and
all that kind of stuff right and if i
i've
i've thought about that you know
if you just added up all the
the incidences of trauma right
and you just condensed it into a period
of time i bet it actually isn't that
much time
but that but the um the the events
themselves
right weren't the thing that was
traumatizing i think the thing that was
traumatizing
was having a horizon
right open to a possibility called
you could be humiliated at any second
right it's those it's those those uh
that
that something is your life or your
identity
or your um was
it was possible at some moment like the
world could just turn
upside down that anticipation of that
possibility
becomes the orientation so you go from a
sense of you really can't listen
right you can only hear what you're
listening for
and if you're in danger right the world
will show up in terms of that
and that's what's so interesting about
and so you know
in in in working through trauma and
myself and like
you know being a part of other people
working through it and all that kind of
stuff it's like
it's so interesting because the
traumatic response
right is an attempt to resolve the
trauma
however the the trauma
requires the world to be indexed in
terms of it
so that i can overcome it so
that's how i think people end up getting
into
like repeated patterns of
re-traumatization
if you will right like you know
somebody's
you know somebody's like has 20 jobs but
they they're in the same conflict in
every job they have the same boss
somehow
right like they get the same
relationship these kinds of things
and it's so interesting because that's
what makes it really tricky
like is
is there's this period where you have to
start to hear
right that you're not hearing
right you you really have to start like
it just seems like that that seems to be
and that's a very
that's a very philosophical right
and i don't think i don't hear this
talked about that much but that's a very
philosophical thing to do right
to and it's it's very difficult too
which is
to begin to hear right that i'm not
hearing
that i'm actually not listening i'm
already
presupposing the world in a certain term
and then on some level i meant in my
anticipation
it draws up to me as a thing to fight
a thing to flee a thing to freeze at
or or or something like that right
and so it seems that the in some sense
it's a little bit like
waking up in lucid dreaming
right where it's a it's a very
deep it's a very deep cognitive
disclosure
to be able to um
hear that i'm not listening
but the moment that you hear that you're
not listening just like when you're in a
dream and you
it dawns on you that you're dreaming is
the moment right
that everything shifts everything is
kind of predicated on that
so i i really appreciate what you're
saying about trauma i think it's
it's a very deep thing um
because i think what a lot of what we're
talking about
i propose is like the difference between
curiosity and wonder
right curiosity
in the technical sense of the word is um
has to do with problem solving
right it's like
you go down this train in in order to
find it like solve a problem
right there's a there's a way in which
curiosity can be
as john talks about if you increase
curiosity
it's not pleasant right if you increase
wonder it becomes more and more and more
pleasant
right or um
something that's nourishing and i think
i think that essentially
one of the things that is
a sign of our deepest nihilism
right really has to do with our absence
of wonder
right um and our that we
that on so in in a big way
and i i really kind of i think i really
take this from heidegger of
it's becoming more and more difficult to
be able to
to see a world such that the response to
that world would be wonderment
right yet
it's in this sense of you know that
i think that the video that you were
talking about uh where i was talking
about with heraclitus is what i'm really
getting
i had no idea i was going to be um
this paper that i'm writing right about
essentially dialogues
right um i had no idea that i'd just be
i'd be it'd be so based on heraclitus
i had no idea that that was going to
happen but i started reading heraclitus
and i'm like whoa
this is this is precisely the logos and
that we don't hear the logos
is precisely the very
the the very you could say the
the basis upon which
the nile the nes not to proclaim
nihilism
the the necessary if you will
nihilism that comes from not listening
to the logos
right it's uh and so i uh
the more i started to look into it the
more i started to really
it's really started to occur to me that
this is why dia logos looking through
logos
right um is so
directly on the mark in terms of
addressing nihilism
right because it is that sense
wonder happens when you have that sense
where
you're looking at some pattern right or
you're looking like say
at artwork and all of a sudden
you start to see the deeper pattern
right you can go oh
this is this this kind of painting this
is this from this time this is a
rembrandt or this is
it starts to disclose itself to you
right
part of that disclosure right that i
think is
so evokes the mood of wonder is that
what's disclosed
right doesn't appear
right it precisely appears and that it
doesn't appear
its flagrancy right is in its
is is is the result of our participating
with something so deeply
that it starts to shine through and
reveals the harmony or the wholeness
of the world in all through all of its
parts but it
but it precisely this is why i think
hearing is such
is the metaphor here or listening is the
metaphor
it's because you don't necessarily see
it with your senses
right it's not immediately given but you
definitely perceive it in fact it's like
the kind of thing that when you perceive
it
it discloses the world as a song
right versus just the notes that don't
make any sense and you start to hear the
song
that is you can't you can only do that
with your whole being
that's you can't have that experience
those kinds of experiences without
it being transformative
of yourself that's where learning
and in the transformation of the self
are just are almost exactly the same
thing
on some level i've been kind of
realizing
it's one of those it's it's and of
course here's the fractal right
of i'm like oh this is why
this is why i've been interested in all
this stuff
it's like oh the sense of the of the
logos of of being able to gather
yourself
right with gathering as such in such a
way that
psyche in the greek sense is your kind
of your constitutional openness to the
logos right
like as you start to comport yourself
like what you're talking about comport
yourself to the world
such that you're listening into what
isn't apparent
right but beckons to you in a cultivated
sense of intelligibility
and then as you do that and you have
more of those experiences
it it starts to um
it starts to invite more of the
experience everywhere which is what i
think you're saying it's like
reading heidegger
it's not just about reading it's not
just about reading books
right you read a couple of pages of
heidegger and you walk
out and you walk in your neighborhood
it's a different neighborhood right
there's a it it's in the it it deeply
affects the way that you participate in
the
world in a co-reflective opening way
but as heraclitus says it is possible
just to listen to me
not the logos right and i think that's
the difference between hearing and
listening
right there there is a way where
yeah right i can i can live within the
measure
the measures measurement of the logos
it's measure
right it's forms it's it's um in some
sense it's intelligibility
right and i can kind of
i can participate in it i can carry it
on i can
but with without actually listening to
the source of it
um and it's that listening to the source
of it which i think is
innately human it is what it is to be
human
right is that we are the beings right
that can in some sense
hear the hear
that uh
you we can hear the song of the universe
right it it becomes hearable in our
constitution right now that very
openness
is also the same openness that made it
possible to not hear it
right and that's what's interesting is
like the very freedom
right that constitutes a makes us able
to to
hear the being of beings to hear the
the wholeness of the universe
in the particular situations of suchness
right that same openness is also
the moment freedom becomes possible is
the moment that prison could become
possible
right and we can forget about it so
yeah yeah i mean even in the course of
listening to you speaking i can move
between
being a space for the emergence of guy
and then dropping back a layer and being
like well how's the interview going
or like what's you know i can become
like much more aware of
my immediate um
spatial environment and this is partly
to do with zoom
um and it's
it was something interesting which came
up with uh my girlfriend was that
um she would notice part of the fruits
of this just when you were when you were
there was a certain moment where you
talked about like yeah and
some of the fruits of this and you
smiled i was like
i bet if i asked about that i bet that's
talking par one of the fruits is is this
relationship that you're in now right
yes to a large extent she watched the
podcast and pulled me through
the internet into um a shared reality
so congratulations my friend i'm really
happy to hear
thank you guy um
it's very very exciting yeah
i bet enlivening
a lot of things a lot of dancing
[Music]
but one of the things that she noticed
was
um there was a different way of me
seeing her when we were speaking
and there was a way in which i could be
seeing and it was like
her she is emerging and appearing and
then there's a way in which my vision
would almost go
through her and backwards into me
um and so that's the that's the
what was the distinction you said just
now it was like the
the listening and the
hearing and listening hearing and
listening
yeah so i can be i can be
um hearing you and seeing you
but i'm somehow elastically in the past
and then the past is present through
what i'm seeing in the same way that
the dream that you have the disturbing
dream that you have
can kind of come
through into your conscious day um
and manifest and shape the reality that
you experience
um and so you were saying earlier
this is something that i'm still
unpacking
and it's something to do with
the relationship between the trauma
and the body and time
and this sense in which
which i can be not fully present to the
present
present to the logos of what's actually
going on
in in in the sense that there's
the way that you talked about these
events um
i mean there's different kinds you can
have a sort of singular event
which has an explosive um
quality to it and i think that this
actually
has a false pay toll which
affects the fabric of space-time as we
experience it as embodied beings
so it's like you're going back along the
kind of
roots of your being into the past and
these events
can it's a little bit like um if you
ever
have seen an explosion take place
underwater
or inside of a ballistics gel it's like
it's contained within the thing
but there's a real energy stored in
those events
um and then you can also have more kind
of
you know like you were saying like
anticipatory
or anxiety can be a trauma as well
in the sense that you're anticipating
something happening
so much that it sinks deeply into your
being
but this is this is somehow key to
understanding our temporality
um that we can be not
fully present in that our bodies are
like
containers of all of the of the past um
[Music]
it's so interesting too it's like i mean
like one of the clearest examples of
that for me
was and this resulted in my marriage
right really
um was
for the first three four years i would
have this experience
that was so obvious to me that um
my girlfriend at the time my wife now
was attacking me
and and of course i'm not going to
tolerate being attacked right i don't
want you to tolerate being attacked so
it's just obvious i'm going to
i'm not going to tolerate it and then i
would hear her
say things like no it's it's
like you turn it into that like if you
would just
i'm she's saying i'm not attacking you
i'm
basically saying i'm in pain or
something like that right whatever
whatever it was
and there was some
there was a moment where there were like
a number of moments where
i got a sense a whiff
of that
i could actually be in a hallucination
right um that in in
precisely the degree in which
it occurred as absolutely real was
almost
the thing that made it so was able to
let me be suspicious of it
and also starting to see that
like if what's at stake
right because i i mean i i loved her
more than i've loved anybody right and
when when there was that sense in which
what if it was like something like what
if
what if i
leave this relationship the person i've
loved more than anyone else in my whole
life
and what i actually left was my own
projection
right like so this is something about
the there's a leverage there that
started to kind of
come in and there was this leap where i
actually kind of had to just
take it on faith on some level
um of that i'm actually not experiencing
what
my whole my whole um
being is telling me that i'm
experiencing
and it was so interesting because
there'd be a moment where
and i would just be like all right i'm
gonna just respond as if i'm not being
attacked
right and in that i realized i noticed
i'm
the first thing i'm confronted with is
that i'm frozen and i had no idea how
frozen i was
right and then i start to move
towards her in a loving way or in this
way
and instantly it it completely went in
another direction
it like went to more intimacy and
in very quickly like
and i i remember experiencing that i'm
like
oh you're whoa how the hell did that
happen
and it was true it's like i i was
there was a part of my being that and it
become it
because i grew up in in an environment
right
that i didn't i couldn't hear the
horizons that i was
kind of you could say for having right
that had her show up in those situations
show up to me in that way
it was just reality and
that little that little spark of doubt
that little sense of being open to
hearing something different
right and then responding to
with that difference in such a way like
instantly
everything it's like the whole thing
shifted
and then you know i would have these
experiences where we'd get into another
interaction
and i'd remember that last experience
right
and i'm like but i couldn't find it i
couldn't find the
i couldn't find the the button
that it would have me respond as if i'm
not being attacked right
um and i would think to myself am i
crazy right now
or was i crazy then right and then at
some point i just started to
it was like a percep perceptual shift
where i just
i just started caring about
assuming that what she was saying is
that one she loved me
right and two something was hurting
and then so just respond to it right
unfreeze and respond and then i would
and then the whole thing would open up
and it was so interesting because it was
this this whole period where it felt
like i was coming out of a
mirage of some kind right um a
hallucination of some kind
and then it it and it was less about
really knowing what to
do it was more like a place to sit
right and then i just found myself
sitting
or relaxing back into myself
and it was just there that perception
that openness was just there
and then it's like now we're married
we haven't like had a we haven't had a
fight like that in like
three and a half years
it's really interesting
love is powerful stuff yeah
at the level of
what the level of that moment um
one of the real complexities that comes
out of this
is gaslighting and so
and i had experiences of this
working through is like you are
in that elastic back into the past thing
so you drop into a very heightened state
of vigilance or sensitivity
to the people around you and then they
are just
being their normal slightly
dysfunctional selves or whatever
um and then
when you face a choice as to whether you
presence and articulate it or not
um because a lot of people they choose
to just like
keep it in and not presence it and that
is almost guaranteed to
to prevent its resolution but
if you do presence it and it's
absurd or something in the context of
where you're at
the other people might choose to just
deny that it's happening um and
improperly related to they can get
they can unintentionally gaslight you
by saying what you're experiencing isn't
real and this actually leads down
an even more
a worse path which is trauma combined
with
a lack of trust in the reality
that you share with other people um
and conversely it's that is that love
and trust that you're describing
which affords the right presencing of
the thing
so you can be feeling it and then you
can make the affirmative step
to presence what it is
and if the person uh loves you
and there's an adequate degree of trust
developing between the two
of you then um
you can just allow it to be there and
then you can sort of begin to work
within and around it and start to sort
of disclose
the wider reality that is present
and not contained within this and then
suddenly you get that
um quite radical shift
and it's like i was in a bad trip
and i've broken out of it and now i'm in
a different palpably different
experience of reality
and and this is so
ontologically deep it's so deep to the
level of my experience of being
that it's like
it's not just that what was immediately
salient in my landscape was
thoroughly diminished and it's not just
the
sense of the depression of the pulling
down of the something you can't quite
get away from
it's also that the future
seems to narrow as well and the past
perhaps enlarge or is more important
um and so
that's a ta telltale sign
i've come to recognize is
in there and they think this is just the
case with emotions right
like usually the more intense the
emotional experience
if you notice the feeling of forever and
always comes with it
right like when you're really depressed
right there's that experience of
not only am i depressed but
and not only is it totally but
it's always been and it's always
going to be
and it's obvious and then if i try if i
try to conjure up a memory
inside of that depression that memory
right of of some time when i wasn't
depressed
just occurs as oh i was obviously just
full of i was delusional right
it's that if there's something about the
totality
and i think what heidegger really talks
about with mood mood
right is the we have these kind of
ontological moods
right that attune us and reveal to us
how things seem right and
they really are reality enforcing in
some
in some way and i think and i think
about this is like
you're right this is where this is where
relationship
right and things like safety and
friendship and um in cultivating that
this is how we become who we are is
through our contact with other people
right it's it's i mean we are
on some level i feel like i am
constituted by all of the conversations
of my life
right on such a profound way right
um and so for me the key
thing was is really
trusting that my wife actually loved me
and the in the thing that i would lose
and it makes sense because
when i was a kid the world would just
turn like you would just
suddenly turn and all of a sudden i was
in hell and everything was in danger
right
and it was this experience of the people
in my life that were caring for me
all of a sudden were like
not like not only not caring for me but
right hurting me
and that one
benevolence right when people experience
benevolence from other people
right that one whoo that one
is tough to recover from so it was this
kind of
there was this kind of sovereignty that
i had to
muster up in that of i really had to
choose
to be willing to see that
she loved me right and
and it was in that kind of faith right
and stepping into that
right that the moment that i did and i
responded
to her and not not that
complex right was it was so insane it
was it was the moment everything would
we just dropped in and i also realized
like oh my god
like i can actually
there's a way in which when i get
triggered
right like
and i get this sense that you don't love
me or you don't really care about me
right a whole the whole world changes
but conversely when i can kind of come
into contact and
actually feel into no
you at the deepest level you love me
right
and attuned to that was the
was in in this instance what i'm talking
about was the difference that made all
the difference
for me and this is why one of the things
that i'm
i'm
i feel um
one of the things that drives me to
continue
to cultivate circling as a practice is
that i think on some level circling is
the practice
of that sense of um philia
right that sense of a deep kinship
and friendship right in being gathered
together and cultivating that um
is why i think is the very basis of
philia sophia philosophy
right that they really kind of go hand
in hand
um is this cultivating friendship and
kinship
and community and developing ways to let
people know that you
actually do care about them right and
you're cared for
and having your heart be open to people
and having that sense of safety and and
bring in in
in making it like i think the thing i'm
i really i think is really important
is and what circling i believe does is
it well it does do this it takes that
out of the back office in the
psychotherapist room
and and starts to bring it actually
with the possibility of a social
practice
that we can that we can actually be
attuned to
right because i think it's that safety
and that kinship that affords us to be
able to open
up to the veil what's beyond the veil
right those horizons of intelligibility
is through friendship
and your therapist
doesn't love you by necessity of
of what that occupation and what that
field and what the understandings of
that whole system of
a way of relating to the person
right it's not about that it's it's a
it's a professional it's constrained and
it doesn't have mutuality and all those
things
i've never actually tried therapy but
i've heard so many
god-awful experiences from so many
people that i have to wonder what's
going wrong
there's something
so there's something in the
experience of trauma and trauma
resolution which tends to bring out
shamanic
kinds of capacities in people which
seems to be a seeing
through um
the surfaces of other people
at an embodied level um
which is connected with the love in some
way
and what i'm with the other piece that i
want a presence
is that when you've established that
trusting loving relationship with your
wife
or with somebody in your circle some
intimate relationship
and you
drop back in your body to the time
period
in which the trauma occurred and
represents it in the present
my sense is that the love the love
as a kind of multi-dimensional
ontological
force is somehow going backwards
in time to that
moment yeah like it's
yeah like the the release of
the energy the energetic payload
of the traumatic experiences
is concurrently the
the sending backwards of the love to the
event
when you are having these encounters
with people and i'm
sure you've had something similar
somebody presences something from
the past completely raw and with all of
the emotional payload with it and you're
able to
give love to it in the present moment
[Music]
why aren't you sending love backwards in
time
because the the body is is existing
um trans temporally right
right doesn't we experience is
constituted psychedelically
of the satin setting of all of the past
experiences
the associations and the dreams and
the
and so the work the work is occurring
trans
trans temporally yeah this can also
happen collectively with like
you know sort of there are people who go
on reconciliation missions of like
going and seeking forgiveness from some
people that their ancestors had wronged
and there are these big emotional events
of of
the long long held um
[Music]
emotional traumas even of many many many
centuries held
yeah yeah totally and it's
i'm i'm really liking this how you're
this bringing this sense of temporality
into it
because it does really have the um
it does have a healing power right
in in very much the same way we were
talking about this i think before we
started recording
about when someone has an insight
right i i kind of noticed like when
somebody has an insight
there's this thing that they do with
their eyes first it's like
like this and then at some point they
start to do this
with every time i've asked
what what are you doing there they're
actually picturing
their past right and
and and usually because an insight
is revelatory of the frame right
it's not like it necessarily like a
discovery
out in front of you it's more like an
insight to
what was concealed in its nearness but
constituting right
and so when you when you have one of
those
frame psycho-emotional frame
seeing then just like in
bruce's willis's uh movie the sixth
sense
right where he's dead the whole time and
no one knows it then he recognizes
right at the end and he goes all the way
back to the first scene in the movie and
scene by
scene you see the whole time that you've
been watching that
he was dead and it was obvious
just unconcealed and
like and that's a great example of how
identity shifting that can be
um and i i really kind of feel that
there's
that there's there's something about um
there's something about a ground of of
of phylic love right of really being in
it with somebody
like and because it's interesting
because that's definitely my experience
i have clients and stuff and i've had
clients that i've had for years and
like so there's a professional
relationship
but my experience is that when we're
together i like i become friends with
all of them
like i i fall in love with my clients
right it's like it's not
in fact i find that it you could say
it's effective to the degree
that i'm really in it with them and
having the insights with them and like
in being deeply affected and changed in
the interaction
and sharing that as well right um
those that kind what that seems to
create
is uh seems to be the soil
that um allows us to open up to positive
traumas
right because if you think about it like
the difference between
a trauma and like a spiritual experience
is structurally very similar right
it's like you know you have a
recognition of the unity that's been
like that you've been disconnected from
your whole life
and it just it questions all of your
assumptions about who you were and what
it was
and all of a sudden you're now
spiritually traumatized in
a way that you wish you always were
that there's an openness to um
it almost i think it almost does the
reverse right
in this connection to connection
yeah yeah yeah where you
you start to have the kind of listening
that you're talking about that you walk
around in the world with
right where it's like there's a certain
level where you
find yourself listening for what you
don't know
right like
i would imagine it's just because you've
been
like ontologically positively
traumatizing yourself now for
less that there's a in whereas trauma is
something like
my for having is i'm already
gathering the world in terms of it and
then responding to it
i think with you know these kind of deep
ontological disclosures it does it
almost does the same thing in reverse
where it's like
i actually surrender my four havings
and i listen for for something i can't
know before and attune to that and be
attuned by that
they're very they're very similar right
the machinery is very similar
yeah yeah i feel that
yeah we're gonna have to expand on that
one in a future conversation guy
i look forward to it this has really
been fun i
don't know i really enjoyed our
conversation and
i felt what i do what i was enjoying
about it was
that sense in which we're both yeah like
i think that conversation in some sense
exemplified
the content that we were talking about
like you could tell at certain moments
where you're talking whereas like
i could feel you and myself just at the
edge
of what i understood in it kind of
coming into articulation
right and time disappeared and
your logos i think we're breaking new
ground with this
and uh yeah there's no one i'd rather be
presencing these um
insights into trauma with so i think
we're
we're actually there is something
emerging out of these conversations and
we're kind of
we're getting at something quite um
metaphysical and juicy and
uh profound so look forward to
continuing it really
great to have you on guy hang our
friendship my friend
likewise
you